- [Instructor] Next up, I've got a really fun demo for you.
We're going to talk
about how you can use ChatGPT
to Automate Tasks in Excel
By Generating VBA Scripts and Macros.
So for this demo, what I've got here is a list
of some of the top earning movies of all time.
It's stored in a macro-enabled Excel workbook,
but you can see that it's a little bit messy, right.
My row heights are all over the place.
My column widths aren't fit properly,
and basically my goal is to clean and polish this up.
Maybe add some alternating row highlights with the goal
of exporting this as a static PDF that I can share.
Now, that's certainly possible to do manually
or just take a few steps,
but if this is something that I'm going to do again and again,
it makes it a great candidate for VBA automation.
So let's pop into ChatGPT.
Let's describe exactly what we're looking for
and see if it can produce AVBA script that we can use.
Alright, so let's go ahead and plug
in a description of what we're looking for.
Be very descriptive and clear here, right,
I have an Excel worksheet named top movies
containing a table with the following fields, title,
genre country rating, IMDB score and gross revenue.
Can you please generate AVBA script to autofit
all rows and columns,
bold the first row, highlight every other row,
and save it to my desktop using this file path as a PDF?
And because I'm not really strong with VBA,
I've also asked it
to provide clear step-by-step instructions.
So let's see how this goes.
All right, so far so good.
It says I can help you with that.
Here's a step-by-step guide to creating a VBA script,
that will do all of those steps that we described.
It's writing the script now.
You can see some comments in here.
Really nice that it's commenting the code,
making it nice and clear,
and then it's giving us kind of
all of those steps that we'll need to follow
and this is looking good so far.
So basically we're creating a sub-routine export as PDF.
We're setting variable names for the worksheet
and the string.
This is where we're autofitting the rows and columns.
This is where we're formatting the table with those kind
of highlights every other row.
This is where we're saving it as a PDF.
You can see that it's used the file path,
it's named at top movies PDF, which makes sense.
And then this is really nice too at the end,
it's popping up a message box that's going to say,
worksheet saved as PDF on the desktop,
which is a nice touch as well.
So this is looking great.
Let's go ahead and copy this code
and let's jump back into our Excel workbook
and we can either use F11
or head to our developer tab
to open up the VBA dialogue box
or window right here and right here in sheet two top movies.
Let's go ahead and view the code
and paste that code that ChatGPT produced right here.
So let's go ahead and give this a shot.
I don't think I need to necessarily change anything here
at least right off the bat.
Let's go ahead and save that, close the editor.
And now is a nice little touch
what I'm going to do is insert a little box here
kind of like a button that we can use.
Add some text, export as PDF
and we'll format that a little bit like so
and then I can right click.
We're going to assign a macro
and that's the sub-routine or the macro
that ChatGPT just produced, export as PDF, press OK.
And now drum roll please,
if I click this button
what we should see, again, is the columns and rows autofit.
We should see every other row get highlighted.
We should see that top header row get formatted in bold.
And most importantly, it should export that data set
as a static PDF on my desktop.
So cross your fingers, let's give it a click.
There we go.
We get that message box.
It says worksheet saved as PDF on the desktop.
We can see right here the columns did autofit.
The rows autofit, header row is bold.
We've got that alternating highlighting, so far so good.
Now, let's go ahead and check our desktop and look at this,
we've got a PDF called Top movies, and when we double click
there is our formatted data set
that ChatGPT helped us produce.
So overall, I was really, really impressed by this example,
especially as someone who doesn't have a ton
of experience writing VBA code.
This probably would've taken me closer to 20
or 30 minutes of trial and error
or searching online tutorials to produce this same code.
But ChatGPT gave it to us in about 30 seconds,
which is pretty unbelievable when you think about it.
I love that it added code comments.
I love that it included the file path.
It was nice
that it added those clear step-by-step instructions.
Just a great shortcut, especially for non-coders
who come across the need to use VBA for automation.