- [Instructor] Alright,
so one use case that I've been exploring
that I'm really excited about
and impressed with is using tools like ChatGPT and Bard
to collaborate on things like data prep
and exploratory analysis.
It's such a great way
to leverage the conversational nature of these tools
and actually learn quite a bit along the way.
So let me show you an example of what this might look like.
Here in ChatGPT, I'm going to drop in a prompt like this.
"I just exported a raw CSV file containing web traffic data.
Could you please act like a data quality assurance engineer
and give me a step-by-step plan to help me QA
and prepare my data for analysis?"
So you can see I'm really trying to set clear context here
with this prompt.
I'm describing the type of data that I'm analyzing.
I'm specifying the role that I want ChatGPT to play,
and I'm providing clear guidance
on the type of output that I'm looking for,
a step-by-step plan.
So let's go ahead and give this a shot
and see how this does.
So, of course,
I'd be happy to help you.
Here's a step-by-step plan that you can follow.
Understand the data, validate data integrity,
follow these data cleaning steps
for handling missing values, duplicates,
got some data transformation steps here,
like parsing or aggregating the data,
look at data formatting,
consistency and integrity,
check for outliers,
document the data.
That's a nice one.
And then finally, once you've completed the QA process,
you can then explore the data further
by visualizing it and so on and so forth.
Love this note at the end.
Remember to keep backups of your original data
and work on a separate copy during the QA process
if you need to refer back to the original data.
So overall, really happy with this response.
It's really thorough.
It does truly hit on some of the most important data prep
and QA tasks that you need to be aware of,
along with some that maybe you weren't.
So really, really solid start.
So maybe you start following these steps
and you do find some missing values,
well, you could follow up,
and say, "Hey, I see some missing values.
How should I handle them?"
And now ChatGPT, again,
because it has all of that context,
it's going to say,
yep, handling missing values is an important step.
It depends on the nature of the data
and the specific analysis goals.
Here are a few common strategies,
removing rows,
imputing values for different types of data,
flagging missing values with a binary column,
or using your domain expertise
to either figure out how to impute them
or decide whether they should be kept or removed.
Again, some good best practices here.
Remember, the chosen approach
should align with the characteristics of your data
and the analysis objectives.
And you should always document and communicate the method.
Love this response.
This is exactly the type of guidance
that I would give an actual student or learner
in the real world.
So overall, great output there as well.
And now let's take it kind of one step further,
and say, all right, now my data's looking good.
Now, can you provide a plan
for conducting some data profiling
and exploratory analysis in Excel?
It's going to give us another plan here.
It's going to talk about common data profiling tools,
calculating summary statistics,
like sums, averages, mins, max counts,
some data visualization advice here,
some tips for filtering and sorting,
using relationships if you're working with multiple tables,
validating the data, documenting.
So again, really good tips.
I like that it gives you examples
of specific formulas and functions
or tools that can help you do these things.
And this is really just an example
of how this type of conversation can go,
but really thorough.
It's very accurate from my experience.
And again, it's a great way
to kind of learn these best practices
as you're using these tools.
So for this one, let's go ahead
and actually test the same conversation flow in Bard
and see how it compares.
All right, so we'll start with that same first prompt.
Just exported the raw CSV file containing web traffic data.
And let's see what we get back from Bard.
All right, so here's a step-by-step plan,
review the data dictionary,
check for missing values, check for duplicates,
data integrity,
clean it, prepare it.
So covering a lot of those same kind of key tips
that we saw from ChatGPT.
It's giving some additional tips here,
use a variety of tools,
be proactive,
get help from a data expert.
I like that one.
So pretty similar.
I like that response as well.
No complaints there.
Let's kind of add our follow up prompt here.
I see some missing values. How should I handle them?
All right, again, similar response.
So you can delete them, impute them.
Here are different types of imputation methods.
And then it offers some tips here, right?
Be aware of the limitations, test different methods,
consult with an expert.
Again, pretty similar response here compared to ChatGPT.
And then let's do our final prompt here,
just like before.
Provide a plan for conducting some data profiling
and exploratory analysis.
All right, so this is what data profiling is.
This is how you could do some data profiling in Excel.
Kind of weird here.
It's formatting this like a code snippet,
but it's actually just text.
It's telling me use data analysis tools,
use conditional formatting,
not really giving me any clear or actionable guidance there.
Same story with this snippet.
Little bit odd.
It's telling me use pivot tables, charts,
analysis tool pack,
use multiple methods, be iterative,
again, get help from an expert.
Not really impressed with this output.
I think this is where the difference
between the two tools is really starting to shine.
ChatGPT was a little bit more thorough
and a little bit more specific.
And I love that it offered actual formulas and functions
and tools that I could apply,
whereas the response from Bard is a little bit more generic.
But overall,
I got to say I'm pretty happy with these outputs.
At the very least,
they do cover a ton of best practices
and important considerations when it comes to data QA
and EDA,
things like missing values, data types, outliers,
normalization, so on.
I love the conversational nature here,
which allows you to really guide the conversation
and focus on specific relevant topics.
And to be honest,
I think this would be a pretty good roadmap
for an analyst to follow,
especially if you have the technical chops
to actually use all of the tools and techniques
that it recommends.