- [Instructor] Hey everybody. In this video,
we are going to talk about prompt engineering.
You may have heard the term prompt engineering
in the context of AI tools,
we're going to walk you through what that means,
and then finish with some tips
so that you can write great, effective prompts.
Don't worry, this is all pretty simple,
and we'll walk you through it step by step.
So first, a prompt is a question or a set of instructions
that is going to serve as the input for AI tools
like ChatGPT or Google Bard.
And prompt engineering is the practice of writing prompts
that are going to generate the most effective
and accurate responses.
So here's an example of a prompt.
This is the question that you're asking of the AI tools
or the instruction that you're giving.
It doesn't have to be a question,
it could be some direction.
You could see the example,
"Can you please explain how the OFFSET function works
in Excel?"
And you'll get back a response like this.
The responses will vary,
this is an example from ChatGPT.
Google Bard works the same way,
the other AI tools work the same way.
The main thing we want you to get here
is the concept of a prompt and a response,
and then our tips and best practices
for writing really good prompts
are to be as clear and specific as possible.
Try to include context and any examples
if that's easy to do.
Establish roles for the specific use cases
you're working with.
Set the tone or the level of complexity.
And then understand the limitations of the model.
We'll walk you through each of these tips
and we'll do an example of a prompt,
and then we'll improve that prompt
by adding a little bit more context here.
Our pro tip here is to not get bogged down
trying to nail the perfect prompt on the first try.
These tools work so quickly
that it's really easy to refine and iterate
if you don't like the quality of your response.
So, try to write a good prompt,
but don't spend too much of your energy
trying to figure out if your prompt is perfect or not,
just get in there and see what you get back as a result.