- [Lecturer] In this video, we're going to walk you through
another tip for prompt engineering to get better results
from AI tools like ChatGPT and Google Bard.
This time we're going to be talking about setting the tone
which can have a major impact on what you see as a response.
You could see an example here where we just say
explain regression analysis, but what does that mean?
Are we explaining regression analysis
to somebody that's really technical?
Are we explaining it to a four year old?
The more context you can give the AI tools in terms
of how you want it to talk, the level things like that,
the better it's going to do at giving you an output
that matches what you really want.
So here in the improved prompt you can see,
we say explain regression analysis in two sentences
to a C-level executive at a marketing agency.
So here, it's not going to go as technical.
It's giving you kind of a quicker soundbite
about what regression analysis is,
and it's going to be more appropriate for that audience.
Our pro tip here is to include something
in the prompt that says, explain it to me
as if you are explaining it to X, Y, Z.
And that could be a child, it could be somebody
who's non-technical, somebody who isn't a data expert.
And in this way, you can control the tone
and the complexity of the response that you're getting.
So try to keep this in mind.
Being prescriptive about the tone can really have an impact
on your results and can help you get a response
that's going to be the most appropriate for your audience
or for the problem that you're trying to solve.