- [Instructor] So we've talked about
how to use tools, like ChatGPT and Bard,
to generate or interpret Excel worksheet formulas.
Now let's take it a step further
and see if we can use those tools
to generate DAX or M Code as well.
So for this demo,
what I've done is loaded up a simple movie table
into Excel's data model.
You can see I've got movie titles here,
along with fields like genre, country, rating,
IMDB score, and gross revenue.
Now suppose we want to do some analysis
and understand average IMDB scores
for different combinations of genre and rating.
Well, one way to do that
would be to use a PivotTable, like so.
You can drop it right here into our worksheet.
Let's go ahead and activate our Field list.
And suppose we care specifically
about the average IMDB score.
Go ahead and change the Field Settings
from Sum to Average for PG-13 rated films specifically.
we'll filter down to just PG-13, and only for Action titles.
Filter, genre equals action as well.
So that gives us our answer.
The average IMDB score
for PG-13 rated action movies is 6.36.
Now let's see if ChatGPT can generate a DAX measure
to produce this exact same value.
All right, so here in ChatGPT,
I'm going to go ahead and paste my prompts.
I'm saying, "I have a table named Movies containing fields
for genre, rating, and IMDB score.
Can you please create a DAX measure
to calculate the average IMDB score
for PG-13 rated action movies?"
Let's see what we get back.
So certainly, you can use the following measure.
Looks like it's using a Calculate function,
which is what I would do.
Average IMDB score
with two filter arguments for genre and rating.
So at first glance, this looks great.
Gives a nice little summary here as well
and reminds us to replace these labels
with the actual table names.
And in this case, these actually match perfectly,
so hopefully, this will be as simple as plug and play.
So let's copy that code,
and let's head back to Excel and give this a shot.
All right, so from our Power Pivot tab,
let's go ahead and create a new measure.
I'm going to paste everything that I had
from ChatGPT right here.
This is actually our measure name.
Copy that, paste it here,
and then delete everything before this equal sign.
And now we should be able to check that formula.
Looks good. No errors.
We can apply a format.
Let's do decimal with two places, and press OK.
And check that out.
The measure that ChatGPT produced was exactly correct.
It gave us that correct answer of 6.36.
So really, really impressed with that use case.
Next up, let's see
if we can actually produce this same value
but this time, using M code inside of Power Query.
So to do that we're going to head
to Data, Queries & Connections.
We see this Movie query where I loaded up my CSV file.
Let's Edit to open up the Power Query editor.
And you can see there have been a few steps applied
to reference the source data, promote the headers,
change some data types,
and I don't want to overwrite all of that.
So what I've found in working with ChatGPT
for M functions is that it's best to go to the Home tab,
open up the Advanced Editor,
and copy all of the existing M code here
and asking ChatGPT to modify this code
instead of creating new code from scratch.
So let's go ahead and copy this.
We'll press Done.
Let's go back into ChatGPT.
Let's paste that code here,
and let's also give it a little bit of context as well.
I'm just going to just add a little prompt
before the code that says,
"Can you please modify the following M code
to add a step calculating average IMDB rating grouped
by genre and rating?"
Now let's cross our fingers,
Submit, and see what we get back.
All right, so far so good.
It says to add a step calculating average IMDB rating
grouped by genre and rating,
you can modify the M code as follows.
Gives us a nice little block of code.
Let's go ahead and copy it.
Let's head back to Excel,
and we can go back to our Advanced Editor.
And I'm just going to select everything, delete it,
and paste what ChatGPT gave me.
It says, "No errors."
That's a good sign.
Press Done and check that out.
It added a step.
It's labeled it Grouped Rows.
And what this is doing is it's calculating
the average IMDB score
for each combination of genre and rating.
So to spot check our action, PG-13,
you could go ahead and sort these, sort them ascending,
Action, PG-13, 6.36.
So there you have it.
Overall, I'd give ChatGPT pretty high marks for this one.
Both the DAX and M examples
that we walked through were spot on.
Granted, they were both relatively simple cases.
Now for more complex queries,
I imagine you need to do a bit more modification.
But nevertheless, I'd be pretty confident using ChatGPT
at least to give you a good starting point,
especially if you aren't completely fluent
with these languages.