- [Narrator] The rate of adoption
for modern AI tools is unprecedented.
ChatGPT became the fastest-growing
online product in history,
reaching one million users in only five days.
So if it felt like ChatGPT came out of nowhere,
it sort of did.
Let's take a look at how other online platforms compare.
It took Netflix 3.5 years to get to one million users.
It took Twitter two years. It took Facebook 10 months.
Instagram took 2.5 months, which is pretty good.
But ChatGPT took a mere five days.
This adoption rate is mind-boggling for any product,
and we're starting to see this cascade
into the AI industry as a whole.
The rapid advancements in AI technology
as well as the success of ChatGPT
have helped lead an explosion
of new app services and players in the field.
We're seeing implementations of AI
in everywhere from text to video, to images,
to code, to speech, 3D modeling, music, and much more.
And we're not necessarily saying that the companies
on this page are going to be what we think are winners
in their given spaces.
But it is worth pointing out,
we're seeing more folks try to leverage AI
and apply them to specific problems than we've ever seen.
So we expect a lot of areas
of traditional work to be transformed
or augmented by these tools.
But in this course, we're going to be primarily focused
on ChatGPT and Google Bard, which are two
of the most popular GPT tools on the market.
ChatGPT was developed by OpenAI
which has a close partnership with Microsoft
and Bard was developed in-house at Google.
ChatGPT made headlines first releasing in November, 2022,
but Google Bard released shortly thereafter
in early 2023 and is a viable competitor.
Both of these tools have a few unique strengths
but are very similar in terms
of benefits and limitations for data professionals.
Speaking of limitations, let's go ahead
and take a look at some common pitfalls
that we can experience when using these tools.