- [Instructor] Okay, so now
that we've covered some important background information
on these tools,
it's time to take a look at how to access them.
It's quite straightforward.
You can access ChatGPT for free at chat.openai.com.
Once you visit that site for the first time,
you'll see a Create your account window pop up,
and OpenAI currently allows anyone to sign up
and use ChatGPT for free.
It's also worth being aware
that there's a paid premium version as well
that gets you access to a more advanced model
and fewer usage constraints.
But we'll be using the free version in this course.
You can either create an account by using an email address
or by connecting to an existing Microsoft or Google account.
And if you're curious about reading more
from the OpenAI team on ChatGPT,
you can go to their blog at openai.com/blog/chatgpt.
It's very straightforward to get started.
Google Bard is quite similar.
You can access Google Bard for free at bard.google.com.
Google does require that you have a Google account,
so if you already have a Gmail account,
you can use that to sign up.
And if you don't have one,
you'll be prompted to create one on the page.
Google made Bard available for free
in May 2023 in most countries,
and if you want to read more about Bard,
you can go to bard.google.com/faq.
So if you want to get started with these tools
and work alongside us,
go ahead and take a few minutes to get set up,
and you'll see John in the next section.