- [Instructor] All right, so for our next demo,
what we're going to practice doing is actually pasting data
directly into ChatGPT and seeing if it can use
that sample data to help produce Excel formulas.
So this will be a little bit of a shortcut,
so that we don't have to necessarily describe
our data set perfectly in words.
So in this case, we're working with
a small sample of customer records.
We've got about 25 customers listed here.
First names, last names, city, state,
date of birth, and email address.
And what we're going to do is just copy and paste
this entire sample into ChatGPT.
We're going to ask it to write a formula for us,
and then we're going to take it a step further
and see if it can actually interpret
and analyze the data that we've provided it.
Now you can just simply copy and paste
the data straight from Excel,
but I found better results saving the data as a CSV,
opening it in a tool like Notepad,
and pasting the data from there.
So here's the data opened up in Notepad,
you can see the comma separated values.
This may just make it a little bit easier
for ChatGPT to digest.
So let's go ahead and copy that, and let's jump into ChatGPT
And we could go ahead and paste that right here.
Now I'm going to jump back up to the top.
I'm going to shift enter to add a couple lines,
and this is where I want to add my actual prompt
with what we're looking for.
So first thing I want to do is describe what we've given it,
and then ask for a formula.
So I've said, here's a sample
of customer data containing 25 records.
Could you please write an Excel function
to extract only the username from the email column?
In other words, we want a function that's going to pull all
of the characters before the at symbol in the email field.
So I'd expect to get something back using
functions like left and find or search.
Let's see how well it does.
Okay, it says to extract only the username
from the email column, you can use the following formula.
Perfect, we get left, search, it's referencing cell D2,
subtracting one to remove the extra character.
So I've written a lot of functions like this,
and at first glance, this looks great.
It says this is assuming the first record starts in row two,
you can enter this in F2, and a little description
of how it's actually working, which I think is a nice touch.
So let's go ahead and copy this code,
and see if it gets the job done.
All right, so back in Excel, one thing you may have noticed,
it told us to drop this formula in F2,
which isn't quite right.
We're going to drop it in the first blank column,
which in this case is G2.
And note that we're referencing column D here.
So left of D2, that's not right.
The email field is actually here in column F.
So I want to change that D2 to an F2 in both instances.
Now let's try that, okay, so we get ChristopherRThames86,
NicoleBPerez68.
So there you go, it did work.
It took a couple minor modifications,
but overall, pretty solid.
We can call this something like username.
So that's great, right?
But we didn't really need to paste
the data for something like that.
We could have very easily accomplished the same thing
by simply describing the function that we're looking for.
Let's jump back to ChatGPT,
and see if it can actually analyze
the sample that we dropped in there.
So let's ask some questions to see
if it actually can interpret that data.
First up, we can ask something like,
who is the oldest customer in the sample?
I'm going to intentionally leave this a little vague.
I'm not going to say find the smallest value of the date
of birth column because I want to see if it can interpret
just the natural language here.
So okay, it says, in order to determine that,
need to find the customer with the earliest date of birth,
which is correct, kind of recognize that column.
From this list we can see the oldest customer is
Christopher Thames with a date
of birth of January 16th, 1950.
Let's spot check in Excel.
Here we go, we're sorted, ascending, got Christopher Thames.
January 16th, 1950, so that looks good.
Now let's ask something a little bit tougher.
How many customers do we have
from Texas based on this sample?
Okay, it's going to say we need to examine the state column.
Uh oh, this isn't the state column,
this looks like the city column, that's not right.
And it says from this list we can see
there are three customers from Texas.
I don't know how it's kind of interpreting that.
Let's regenerate and see what we get this time.
Okay, this time it's pulling in both city
and state, which looks to be a little bit better.
But then it says there are two customers from Texas.
Let's regenerate again and see what we get.
Same kind of list here.
Now it's saying there are three customers from Texas,
so you should be starting to sense
a little bit of a red flag here, right?
Which is that clearly ChatGPT has some ability
to interpret the data that we've pasted,
but clearly it is far, far from perfect.
So I've played with this with all sorts
of different sample data sets,
and I continue to see quite a bit
of variability in the responses.
So overall, my take on this use case is that it tends to be
more of a party trick than a valuable tool,
especially for analysis.
This is one of those examples
where ChatGPT's hallucinations can very easily produce
completely incorrect responses.
And in this case, we could easily spot check
since we're working with a very small and simple data set.
But in the real world, that would be pretty unlikely.
So my advice here would be copying and pasting
or providing sample data can be a helpful tool
to help generate formulas
and provide ChatGPT with more context.
But asking it to actually analyze the data sample itself is
something that I don't have much confidence in,
at least at this point.
There are other tools out there like data interpreter
that do this much better,
and I expect this functionality to get stronger
and stronger soon, but at least at this point in time,
use it with caution.