- [Instructor] All right, so for our next demo,
I'd like to explore how we might be able to use tools
like ChatGPT for data visualization.
Now, even though ChatGPT can't currently produce
visual responses outside of code samples, at least not yet,
I'm curious if we can use it
to better understand data viz best practices,
or have it recommend effective visuals
based on some given context.
So let's go ahead and drop in a few prompts,
and kind of grade or score the responses we get back.
So first prompt, I'm analyzing a sample of wine data
and would like to understand the distribution
of wines by price point.
What will be the best way to visualize this in Excel?
Now I'm being very deliberate
about how I've written this prompt, specifically the use
of this term distribution, right?
Because anyone who has expertise in data visualization
should recognize that histograms are widely known
as the clearest and most effective way
to visualize the distribution of values.
So that's what I'm looking for,
that's kind of what I'm hoping to get back
in ChatGPT's response, let's see what it looks like.
All right, so to visualize the distribution of wines
by price point, perfect.
You can use a histogram or a column chart, which is fair.
And then, even though we didn't ask for it,
it's giving us a nice kind of step-by-step guide
for how to actually produce those visuals.
And this is kind of nice, it's giving us a little summary
and description of when you might lean towards
a histogram versus a column chart, right?
Histogram for continuous data,
column chart for discreet or categorical.
I think that's a helpful, nice touch.
So overall, good start. Good response.
Let's try another prompt here.
This time, I'm analyzing data from my website,
and I'd like to show how total page views
and conversion rates have trended over time.
What would be the best way to visualize this in Excel?
Again, I'm being very deliberate
and specific about this prompt.
This time, I'm asking how to visualize two metrics
that are on totally different scales, right?
We have total page views, which is a volume metric,
we've got conversion rate, which is a percentage
or a rate metric, and I'm asking about trending over time.
So in this case, I'm looking for at least some element
of a line chart or column chart to show trending,
and if I were approaching this as a human being,
I would likely use a combo chart, like a line and column
with a secondary axis so that I could show both
of these trends in one visual.
So let's see what ChatGPT comes back with here.
All right, so to visualize that trend,
you can use a line chart.
Okay, here's how you can do it.
Prepare the data, select the data, insert the chart,
customize it, finalize it,
make sure you're using date values, that's a nice touch.
So I'd give this response maybe a B or a C, right?
It got the line chart to show the trending,
but it really didn't recognize the fact
that those two metrics we want to show
will likely be on very, very different scales.
So overall, not bad, not great.
Let's try one more example here.
All right, now I'm analyzing a dataset containing records
of auto accidents, and I'd like to visualize the data
in Excel to show when accidents are most likely to occur
by hour of day and by day of week.
Can you please suggest the best type of visual to use?
So while there are many different ways
you could potentially visualize the data
as it's described here, what I'm hoping to see
is something like a heat map returned,
which in this case, would be a really effective way
to show those accident counts across
those different dimensions, hour of day and day of week.
So let's see what ChatGPT comes up with for this one.
All right, to visualize when accidents
are most likely to occur, perfect.
It mentions heat map, so a combination of heat map
and clustered column, that's kind of interesting.
Personally, I think the heat map alone
can do the trick quite well.
And it says by combining a heat map
and a clustered column,
you can effectively visualize the patterns
of auto accidents based on the hour of day
and the day of the week.
The heat map provides an overview of accident intensity,
while a clustered column helps analyze the distribution
of accidents within each hour of the day.
Pretty good, I like that it landed on heat map,
especially just based on a relatively quick
and simple prompt.
So overall, you know, my take on this use case
is good, not great.
Generally I think ChatGPT was able
to make some smart recommendations here.
Histograms for distribution, line charts for trending,
and heat maps for accident frequencies,
and while it does kind of start to provide some reasoning
into why it's chosen certain visuals,
my recommendation here would be to really continue
to focus on learning data visualization best practices
and design theory from the experts
rather than expecting ChatGPT to play that role.