- [Instructor] All right.
So we just took a look at a ton of different ways
analysts can use ChatGPT and Google Bard
in their day-to-day work.
And some of the demos,
ChatGPT and Bard performed amazingly well
and gave us exactly what we needed.
In other cases, they fell flat or even lied to us.
But the point of these demos wasn't to show
how accurate or inaccurate these tools are,
but rather that tools like ChatGPT
will change the way data professionals work.
Even though these tools will never be perfect,
they're going to continue to get better.
So we expect there to be more cases
where they perform exceptionally well
and fewer where they fall flat.
And so analysts who are able to leverage these tools
will be able to stay competitive and excel in the age of AI.
Analysts who shun these tools or stay out of the game
will have a harder time keeping up with their colleagues
that are AI augmented.
And of course, as we saw, AI isn't perfect
and may hallucinate or provide incorrect responses.
Again, we expect this to get better over time
but you still always have to take these responses
with a grain of salt.
And remember that you are ultimately responsible
for verifying the accuracy of the model output.
Prompt engineering can dramatically improve
response quality.
If you want to get good results,
you need to provide good input.
So make sure to be specific, provide meaningful context,
and iterate to provide accurate and relevant responses.
And finally, as we saw, AI tools can be applied
to many types of analytics use cases.
Tools like ChatGPT can help troubleshoot or generate code,
automate tasks and much more.
And before we let you go,
let's take a brief look at the future.
In terms of revolutionizing the way analysts work,
ChatGPT and Bard are only the beginning.
In just the handful of months it's been
since ChatGPT was released,
we've already heard major announcements
from companies like Microsoft and Tableau
on integrating AI tools
into the software analysts use on a daily basis.
So these AI tools are going to be increasingly integrated
with our analytics work.
And just like the internet at the turn of the century,
AI tools will fundamentally change the future of work.
And so our advice for moving forward
is stay up-to-date with new tools and technology.
The AI industry is evolving quickly
so make sure to follow the latest news and developments
from trusted companies and thought leaders in this space.
Be curious but skeptical.
While we expect some amazing new AI developments
in the coming years,
we also expect to see some unrealistic promises
from companies trying to capitalize on the height.
Just as we've seen with every major tech trend
in the past few decades,
we do see some very concrete
and influential improvements in the space
but there's also a lot of people
trying to get in on the hype.
Staying open-minded is going to enable you
to take the best of what's to come,
but staying skeptical is going to help you avoid
some of the traps that these false promises present.
And finally, build a well-rounded skillset.
So at Maven Analytics, we've always preached this
but this has never been more important.
As tools like ChatGPT
begin to automate more complex technical tasks,
focus on developing your uniquely human skills
like problem solving, strategic thinking,
communication, and business acumen.
If you're able to continue to grow in these areas,
then AI is only going to make you better at your job.
AI will not only help you work
through the technical aspect of your job more quickly,
it will also free up a lot of time
for you to focus on the big picture.
So that's going to conclude this course.
We at the Maven team
are very grateful to have had you on board,
and we're looking forward to seeing
how you implement these tools in your day-to-Day work.
If you come up with anything you want to show off,
please reach out to us on social media
and we'll catch you later.