- [Instructor] In this video,
we're going to give you our next prompt engineering tip
to get better results from AI tools
like ChatGPT and Google Bard,
and that's to establish roles.
What that means is you can assign a role
that the AI tool is going to play
and you can also assign a role that you yourself,
as the receiver of the information, is going to play.
So check out this example.
What's the best way to clean data?
ChatGPT comes back with a response here,
but then we can add so much more context
in terms of the role that we are going to be playing,
a new Data Analyst for a retail business.
And then we want the AI tool to play the role
of a Data QA Engineer and provide a step-by-step plan
that we can follow.
So when we establish these roles,
it's more clear to the AI tool
exactly who the audience is,
what you want to be getting in your response,
and it can just really improve the quality
of the result that you get back.