- [Instructor] AI tools like ChatGPT
became widely popular in late 2022,
but they owe their success to more than 60 years
of research and development
in artificial intelligence systems.
Outside of AI research,
we also saw massive surges in computing power,
storage capabilities, data generation, and much more.
There were a number of factors that led to ChatGPT,
but let's focus on the AI research that got us there.
So this chart here shows the increasing complexity
of neural network models over time.
So on our X axis we have time,
and on our Y axis we have the number of model parameters
that specific neural networks had.
And so the term artificial intelligence
was only coined in 1955,
and a few years later,
the first neural network algorithm was implemented.
This model had one parameter,
but there was a ton of interest
in getting machines to mimic human intelligence.
And that led researchers at MIT to develop ELIZA,
which was the first chatbot in the mid-'60s.
And this was not a super sophisticated chatbot
nor was it based off of neural network architecture,
but it did take in human input
and return text as a response.
In the late-'60s, AI research somewhat stalled.
Researchers found some issues
with the original neural network architecture
and researchers were also running into issues
implementing AI systems in practice.
So this led to reduced funding and interest
for a number of years.
AI research really started to pick back up again
in the mid-'80s
after a novel neural network architecture was created.
Multi-layer perceptrons,
which helped solve the issues researchers found
in the late '60s, as well as back propagation,
which was a technique for allowing these algorithms
to solve for their own errors better,
were implemented in the same algorithm,
and this made them much more powerful
and opened up the door to new practical applications.
In the meantime, corporations were starting to get invested
into the artificial intelligence game.
In the mid '90s, Deep Blue,
which was a supercomputer developed by IBM,
beat chess champion Garry Kasparov,
which was one of the first times on a big stage
that AI and computer systems successfully beat humans
at their own game.
Around the same time,
neural networks also showed extreme promise
in document recognition.
It became the go-to method to help understand
what humans had written by hand.
This opened up the door to a widespread array
of practical applications
that had tremendous economic benefit,
and we really started to see a lot more interest
back in neural networks once again.
In the mid 2000s, the first neural network
with deep learning capabilities was developed,
and this is one of the most important breakthroughs
that led to some of the AI tools we saw today.
And so just to point out, from about 1955 to about 2010,
we saw about a two-year doubling
in terms of the number of parameters that models had.
But once we move into the last decade,
we see this number shrink down to four months.
So every four months,
these models are getting twice as complex
as they were before.
We're not necessarily forecasting
that this doubling is going to progress at the same rate.
It may increase,
it may plateau as we see diminishing returns,
but things moved extremely fast in the last decade.
So in the modern era of AI, we kicked this off
by seeing IBM Watson beat humans at "Jeopardy!"
So they were able to understand context of questions
and provide answers at a better rate than humans were.
In 2012, we saw AlexNet, a deep learning model,
set a standard for image recognition.
This is when AI image recognition
started to approach that of humans.
We saw Siri and Alexa launched in about 2014,
and in 2015, Open AI, the creators of ChatGPT was founded.
And in the same year, AlphaGo beat world champions at Go.
This was powered by deep learning,
and Go was considered a much more challenging problem
for computers to solve than chess,
which was a little bit more predictable
in terms of what players could do.
In 2017, researchers at Google published a paper
on transformer layers,
introducing them into neural networks.
Transformer layers were the last key piece
of machine learning research necessary
to create algorithms like ChatGPT.
And from there, shortly after we seen GPT1, GPT2,
GPT3, and finally, GPT4,
all released in about a five-year span.
And in terms of model parameters,
GPT1 had about 100 million parameters,
while GPT4 had over 1 trillion,
representing about a 10,000 times increase
in terms of model complexity.
And we only got to GPT4 because early iterations of GPT
showed extreme promise for solving the problems
that we'll see later on in this course.
And so again, in a span of about 65 years,
we went for the term artificial intelligence being coined
to GPT4 with a trillion parameters being released.
Now let's go ahead and turn our attention to ChatGPT.