- [Instructor] Let's begin by setting some expectations.
First off, this course is designed to be an overview
of how data professionals can use AI tools.
We'll introduce the broader AI landscape
and tools like ChatGPT
and we'll review practical use cases for data analysts,
but we won't be diving deeply
into how these large language models actually work
or give an exhaustive list of everything
that they're capable of.
Next, we'll be using the free versions of these AI tools
for the course demos.
We'll quickly touch on some paid options
and alternative tools,
but the majority of what you see
will be shown using the free versions
of either ChatGPT or Google Bard.
Perhaps most importantly, AI is a rapidly evolving field
and these tools will change very, very quickly.
This technology is moving fast
and that means that existing products are going to change,
new vendors and tools will emerge,
but hopefully, the core concepts
and best practices you learn in this course
will remain relevant.
Last but not least, this course is designed
to be modular to fit your needs.
The first half of the course is designed for everyone.
It's where we'll talk about the AI landscape.
We'll introduce these different tools,
talk about prompt engineering, best practices, and so on.
But the second half is structured
so that you can focus specifically
on the tools you use most as an analyst,
Excel, Sheets, SQL, Power BI, or Python.
Now of course, remember that what you see
on our screens during the demos
won't always match what you're seeing on yours,
especially given how these AI tools actually work,
but our goal is to give you some ideas and techniques
that you can take and apply to your own work.
So with that, we've got a lot to cover.
Let's get started.