- [Instructor] Generative AI systems
are deep learning models
capable of generating original text, images,
and other types of media in response to user prompts.
Large language models,
which is what we're focused on in this course,
are generative AI models
focused on producing text output specifically.
Other generative AI models include DALL-E and Midjourney,
which are used to generate images.
And if you haven't heard of these two tools yet,
I highly suggest taking a look
for Midjourney images on Google.
You'll find some very interesting images
that have been created by AI.
And so just to give us a little bit of insight
into how complex these algorithms really are,
let's take a look at a simple language model.
So maybe the first prototype of ChatGPT
looks something like this.
I prompt the machine "The capital of France is",
and we hope to see
the capital of France is Paris in return.
And so most of us know almost instinctually
that the capital of France is Paris.
But how does the model fill in the blank?
The model doesn't know that Paris is the correct response
but suggests the answer
that it thinks is most probable in the given context.
So 99 times out of 100,
when we see the capital of France is,
the last word there will be Paris.
But this model has to compare Paris with thousands of words
and determine that it had the strongest relationship
with words like capital and France.
And that may seem easy and it certainly is to our brains.
But remember that the word capital has multiple meanings,
that France has had other capitals historically,
and that the blank could also be things like beautiful,
a popular tourist destination, et cetera.
So even though we expect the answer to be Paris,
these models have to rank the probability
that Paris is the correct answer
against thousands, if not hundreds of thousands,
of other options that might have some probability
of being correct.
And when we take that a step further,
our large language model has to do a lot more work.
I could ask, when did Paris become the capital of France?
And ChatGPT replied, Paris became the capital of France
in the sixth century.
But how does the model answer this question?
It looks at millions of documents for similar questions
and related statements,
like "in 508 AD Paris became the capital of France".
It then associates the prompt with these documents
and does its best to mimic the language from the responses.
Since it has an element of randomness
to account for its uncertainty,
if you ask it again,
it will likely tell you something similar but not identical.
And so large language models like ChatGPT
are colossal achievements in machine learning
that model the quote unquote shape of language.
They've looked at so many millions of documents
from the internet and elsewhere
that they're pretty accurately able to associate
these different combinations of words in our prompt
and assemble responses based on the millions
of documents that they've seen.
If you look at early versions of generative AI,
the answers are wildly unpredictable
and often don't make grammatical sense.
But as these models have gotten more complex,
they've gotten closer and closer to mimicking human language
until now we have tools
that seem very credible in this regard.
And just to quickly define what GPT and ChatGPT means,
this stands for generative pre-trained transformers.
These are a type of large language model
trained on massive text datasets
and are designed to generate outputs
that mimic human written text.
So generative means the model generates new
and original natural language text
instead of copying and pasting existing data.
Pre-trained means the model
was already trained on a large dataset
before being fine-tuned to perform specific tasks.
This also enables models like ChatGPT
to be accessed by companies and further trained
to specific needs based on that context.
And finally, transformers,
which were one of the last pieces in deep learning necessary
to lead to ChatGPT.
These came out in around 2017.
But these are a type of deep learning model
that can process sequential inputs
and differentiate the importance
of individual parts of language.
This is also known as self-attention.
And LLMs like ChatGPT are among the most sophisticated
deep learning models ever built.
GPT-4, which currently powers premium versions of ChatGPT,
cost over a hundred million dollars
and took 11 months of computing to train
with some of the most state-of-the-art compute
available to us.
So these are incredibly complex and expensive algorithms
that have unparalleled access to data
and unparalleled complexity.
Now let's go through a quick history lesson
and understand how we got to complex models like ChatGPT.