- [Presenter] Hey, everybody.
In this video, we're going to go through our first tip
for prompt engineering to get better results
from your AI tools.
And that tip is to be clear and specific.
The more specific you are
when you're prompting these AI tools,
the better the result is going to be.
So, let's go through an example.
Here, we've got a question, we're working in Excel
and we want to know how to calculate year over year growth.
The response that we get back is good,
but it could be even better
if we told the AI tool exactly what we are trying to do.
So here's what a better prompt would look like.
You see now we're including the fact
that we want an Excel formula
and we're also telling the AI tool where the data lives
in cells C two through C 100 and cells B two through B 100.
And you see the response here.
It's so much more clear.
It gives us the actual Excel formula, which is great.
And then, it also gives a little explanation of it below.
So keep that in mind.
Try to be as clear and specific
as you possibly can when you're writing these prompts.
And the pro-tip here is
if you're generating code, include details
like your variable names, your data types, your cell ranges,
whatever you can do to be as specific as possible.
It will really help out your response.