- [Instructor] All right, if you are a data analyst
or an Excel user and you're looking for a fun way
to use ChatGPT, here's a great demo for you.
I'm going to show you how you can use ChatGPT
to generate custom sample data sets
that you can use to practice your skills.
So check this out.
I'm going to walk through a couple different examples.
We're going to start with a prompt like this.
"I'm a recently hired web analyst
for an e-commerce business,
looking for sample data that I can use to apply my skills.
Can you please produce a sample data set
in CSV format containing common fields
that web analysts typically encounter on the job?"
Let's see what we get back.
So, "Certainly, here's a sample dataset in CSV format
that contains common fields,
often encountered by web analysts."
And it's producing the data right here.
Looks like we've got columns like timestamp, visitor_id
and so on.
And check this out.
It's actually providing a nice little data dictionary here
with descriptions of the fields that it produced.
Timestamp, id, page_url, referral_source,
device_type, product_category, quantity, transaction_id.
These are actually really, really accurate
and relevant metrics for web analytics.
I actually spent about 10 years working
in a web analyst role, and this is very representative
of the types of data sets that we would analyze on the job.
So that's great. We could just copy the code.
We could dump it into Excel and start playing with it.
Now I want to show a slightly different example,
using a very similar type of prompt
and I'm going to create a new chat for this one.
And this time we're a recently hired data analyst
for an HR firm, again, looking for sample data
to practice with.
Now we can specify,
let's produce a 50 record sample again in CSV format.
And now we want it to contain common fields
that HR analysts typically encounter on the job.
So by default, I think ChatGPT typically produces,
like, 10 record samples.
So we could do 50 or 100.
Generally speaking, we can't provide large data sets here.
So let's give this one a shot.
Right away, it starts producing that 50 record data set.
This time we have HR specific fields,
like, employee id, first name, last name, birthday,
gender, department, position.
Looks like we've got some salaries here as well.
And let's go ahead and let this run its course.
And sometimes you might notice, when you're trying
to get it to produce a lot of code like this,
sometimes it hangs up
and you need to click this continue generating button.
This is going to kind of pick up where it left off
and hopefully get us all the way to our 50 records sample.
There's our 50 records
and it gave us a little summary at the end.
Includes fields like employee id, first, last name,
date of birth, gender, department, position, salary,
start date, and end date.
So that sounds like a pretty good set of metrics
but we all know that in the real world,
the data isn't always this clean and tidy.
So here's a little pro tip for you.
One thing that I really like to do is add a prompt,
that sounds something like this.
"The data we normally deal with is pretty messy,
so I'd like to practice my data cleaning skills as well."
And now check this out.
We're going to ask ChatGPT to modify this data sample
to include some common data QA issues
and also describe what types of changes it made.
Let's go ahead and enter that prompt.
It's going to go ahead and modify the sample data set
and it's going to make these types of changes.
So it's adding missing values,
it's introducing inconsistent date formats.
It's adding some duplicated records,
inconsistent capitalization.
Again, very, very common real-world issue.
Some incorrect salary values and gender values as well.
So this is awesome.
These are real-world data issues
that analysts often encounter in the real world.
So it gives the modified sample dataset
with those described changes.
Again, we can copy this, we can paste it into Excel
and in a matter of minutes,
we've got a great relevant sample data set,
that we can use to practice our skills.
So overall, I had a lot of fun with this demo.
I think ChatGPT did a really nice job
identifying relevant industry specific fields
for the sample data, and it made it very easy to simply copy
and paste that CSV format right into Excel.
And now that's helpful in itself.
But the ability to inject realistic data quality issues
was the icing on the cake for me.
And this is really just scratching the surface
of the types of prompts we could play with
for this type of use case.
Now, the obvious drawback here is that
it's tough to get larger data samples.
In fact, we saw it hang up a few times
even generating just 50 records.
But still, this is a valuable learning resource
and something that I expect will improve quite a bit
as the technology continues to advance.
But in any case, great way to grab some sample data quickly,
so that you can roll up your sleeves and start practicing.