- [Instructor] All right, welcome to the ChatGPT for Excel
section of the course.
In this section, we'll be exploring some of the most common
and powerful use cases for data professionals
to use ChatGPT with Microsoft Excel,
including things like generating formulas and functions,
troubleshooting and diagnosing errors,
explaining complex topics and much, much more.
So here's a quick review of some of the topics and demos
that we'll dig into.
We're going to use tools like ChatGPT and Bard
to help explain complex formulas
or topics to us as if it's our own personal tutor.
We'll also use these tools to generate brand new
worksheet formulas as well as DAX measures and M Code.
We'll see how ChatGPT can help us automate tasks
with VBA macros and custom scripts.
And from there we'll practice loading sample data
into ChatGPT using it to troubleshoot and diagnose
formula errors, practice generating step-by-step tutorials
or roadmaps for things like data prep
and exploratory analysis.
And finally, we'll use these tools to actually
generate industry specific sample data sets.
So our goals for this section, we're going to learn how to use
ChatGPT and prompt engineering to help explain
complex Excel formulas or concepts.
We'll also generate new formulas based on either
text descriptions or sample data that we provide.
We'll generate DAX, M, and VBA code
for things like data modeling, analysis, and automation.
We'll troubleshoot broken formulas or code.
And again, we'll use ChatGPT to actually provide us
with step-by-step plans for data prep,
quality assurance, exploratory analysis, and more.
We've got a lot of really fun topics to dig into.
So let's get started.