- [Instructor] Alright, so for this next demo,
what I want to do is see if we can use ChatGPT
to generate clear step-by-step instructions or guidelines
for conducting some sort of analysis in Excel.
I'm going to walk through two examples here,
starting relatively simple with a basic PivotTable,
and then we're going to try something a bit more advanced
by creating a relational data model using Power Pivot.
And what I want to see is if ChatGPT
can guide us through this process
as if we were a beginner user
without much familiarity with these tools.
So for the first demo, what we've got here
is a basic sample of product orders.
Got order IDs in column A, product names in B,
quantity, price, revenue,
and a categorical field called Order Size,
which is based on the quantity purchased.
Now, suppose we wanted to calculate the average revenue
for each order size specifically.
This is something that's very easy to do with a PivotTable.
Let's see if ChatGPT can walk us through the process.
So what I'm actually going to do is copy
a little sample of the data here,
and now let's jump into ChatGPT.
Let's go ahead and paste that sample here,
and I'm going to shift down,
and add the rest of my prompt like so.
All right, so we're saying I have an Excel table
containing the following fields
from the table we just looked at.
I need to create a PivotTable
showing the average revenue for each order size
formatted as currency, USD.
And then we're saying,
please provide clear step-by-step instructions
for creating the PivotTable using Excel for Office 365,
and here's a sample of the first,
in this case, I think it was 15 rows of data.
Let's see how ChatGPT does with this one.
All right, looking good so far.
So to create a PivotTable
showing the average revenue for each order size
in Excel for Office 365,
follow these step-by-step instructions.
Now, let's see if we can pull these instructions up
side by side with our Excel file,
and see if we can walk through them step by step.
All right, so here we go,
we've got our instructions on the right from ChatGPT,
we've got our Excel sheet on the left.
So open our Excel file, done.
Select the range of cells that includes the data,
including headers.
Control A, there we go.
Go to the Insert tab, boom,
click on the PivotTable button, which is right here.
That opens the create PivotTable dialog box.
Ensure the range is correct, that looks good,
A1 through F101.
Let's place this on the existing worksheet,
kind of right over here in H2.
Step seven, click OK to create the PivotTable, there we go.
Now the PivotTable field list
will appear on the right side, it did.
From the field list, locate order size, drag it into rows.
Easy enough.
Locate Revenue, drag it into Values.
By default, it should already be set to Sum of Revenue.
It is, but now we need to change the summary to average.
So we're going to click that dropdown arrow,
select Value Field Settings, and select Average.
From here, press OK.
And let's see how this is starting to look.
I'm going to scroll over here.
There we go, we've got our order sizes listed out.
We've got our average revenues by order size and our values.
We've gone through the first 13 steps without any issue.
So now I think the last step
was just to format those as currency.
So we're going to right click any value in the values area,
choose Value Field Settings, then Number Format,
or we could skip a click
and just go straight to Number Format,
select Currency from the category list,
choose USD, which is the dollar sign,
select the number of decimal places, which is two,
and then click OK.
So that's step 19,
click OK to apply the currency formatting to the PivotTable.
We've got average revenue of $162 for large orders,
41 for medium, and 8.49 for small, which sounds about right.
And there we go.
It says you should now have a PivotTable
showing the average revenue for each order size
formatted as currency.
I like the caveat here, but in this case,
that actually worked perfectly without a hitch.
That's exactly how I would approach it as an expert.
Great, clear step-by-step instructions.
Now let's push it a little bit further
and see if ChatGPT can effectively give us some guidelines
for something a bit more complicated,
like creating a relational data model.
So for this example, I have a new workbook,
it's called Data Model.
And in that workbook, I have four different tabs.
Each tab contains a table.
This table contains transactions, with a transaction date,
product ID, customer ID, and quantity.
Then I have a calendar table, I have a product table,
and I have a customer table as well.
And each of those tables has a primary key,
in this case, customer ID.
For products, we have product ID
to relate these tables back to our transactions
and analyze all this information together using Power Pivot.
So for this example, what I'm actually going to do
is show you how I would approach this first as an expert,
and then I'm going to provide a prompt to ChatGPT,
and then compare my approach
to how ChatGPT recommends tackling this type of task.
So here's how I would approach it.
I would go through each of these four tables,
I would open up the Power Pivot tab,
and I would add each table to the data model like so.
So I'm starting with transactions.
I'm going to go back to calendar, Add to Data Model,
see, it adds a second tab there,
go to products, Add to Data Model,
and then you guessed it, same story for customers,
Add to Data Model.
So now I've effectively loaded all four of those tables
into Excel's data model.
Didn't have to go through Power Query,
didn't have to do any table imports or anything fancy.
Simply one click from that Power Pivot menu,
and all my data's in here.
Now, really all I need to do is jump into Diagram View
where I can see all four of those tables,
and I can create those relationships
by mapping the primary keys in my lookup tables
to my foreign keys in my data or fact table.
And that's it, now I've got my properly related data model
here in Power Pivot.
I could add a PivotTable
to start analyzing or exploring that data,
but really, it was as simple as that.
So now that we've seen my approach, let's take a look at
how ChatGPT recommends approaching this.
So why don't we do a new prompt here.
I'm going to try to be as clear and descriptive
as I possibly can with this prompt.
So notice I've already kind of precopied samples
from each of the four tables
in that workbook we walked through.
But I'm basically telling ChatGPT,
I've got this Excel workbook, it's called Data Model.
It contains the following tables,
transactions, calendar, products, and customers.
I've included sample data from each table below.
This is a sample from transactions, from calendar,
from products, and from customers.
The reason I'm doing this is to make sure that ChatGPT
can see the primary and foreign keys,
and recommend meaningful table relationships here.
And then I'm saying please provide step-by-step instructions
to add these tables to Excel's data model
and join them together using Power Pivot.
I'm using Excel for Office 365.
So I'm being about as explicit as I possibly can.
Let's see how ChatGPT does.
Alright, so it says to add these tables
to Excel's data model
and join them together using Power Pivot,
follow these step-by-step instructions.
So open the Data Model workbook, great.
Make sure the Power Pivot add-in is enabled.
That's really only relevant for older versions of Excel,
but that's okay.
Click Power Pivot, click Add to Data Model,
choose From Other Sources, select Table, click Next,
go through the Table Import Wizard, choose the Excel file,
import the data, load it to the data model.
Lot of extra steps there that we didn't have to do
because our tables were already stored in worksheets.
And then from there, it's saying select Diagram View,
which we did.
And this actually looks pretty good.
So it's saying drag and drop customer ID from transactions
to customer ID in customers.
That creates a relationship between those tables.
That looks good, that's exactly what we did.
Same story with product ID,
same story with date to the calendar.
And then you can close the Power Pivot window.
So overall, not bad.
Definitely kind of walked you through some extra steps there
in the beginning,
but I think this ultimately would've gotten you
to the right end result.
Let's actually regenerate this again,
'cause I've seen a few different types of outputs
that it's provided.
So same story here.
We're enabling Power Pivot first,
importing the data using Power Query, From Table and Range.
Then we're defining relationships.
This one goes a little bit further
into creating a PivotTable to actually analyze the data.
So again, not bad, not great.
Let's do one more, and see what we get this time.
So again, it's kind of taking us
through the Power Query approach,
which I think is kind of an extra step.
Get & Transform, From Other Sources, From Workbook,
load it, add it to the data model.
So overall, decent response,
not the most efficient way to approach it.
And to be honest, there were a few times
where I ran this query and got totally wacky advice
to start writing custom M queries,
just things that were totally unnecessary here.
So overall, I think this is another use case
that I definitely approach with caution.
It was definitely helpful for getting started
with relatively simple tasks,
like PivotTables, or formulas for instance.
But there were a number of times
where it sent me down the wrong path,
or at least an inefficient path
when I tried to get guidance on things
that were a bit more sophisticated,
even after I spent quite a long time
testing and refining different prompts.
So this is a case where if you don't know better,
you could potentially waste a lot of time
going down unproductive rabbit holes,
or following inefficient roundabout instructions
to accomplish something that could have been done
in a much simpler way.
So my advice here, consider using ChatGPT
as a thought starter for this type of thing,
but you're likely to get better guidance
from online tutorials,
or better yet, by consulting actual experts.