- [Instructor] Hey everybody.
In this video we've got another tip for prompt engineering
to get better results from AI tools
like ChatGPT and Google Bard.
And that tip is to provide as much context
as the AI tool needs to get you the exact result
that you need to solve your problem.
Let's go through a quick example.
So we've got this first original prompt saying,
"What are common supply chain KPIs?"
And that works, but look at what comes back
when we give a lot more context saying,
"I'm a data analyst working on supply chain analytics
for a multinational distribution company.
What KPIs should I be analyzing for each metric
please include a formula showing how it's calculated."
And then we even give an example
of what we'd like to see.
Here as an analyst who's trying
to get up to speed on a new industry,
this output that you get in the result is just fantastic.
It's exactly what you would want to see as a first pass
and then you could drill deeper
into each one of them after
to help yourself get up to speed.
So remember, when you're using these AI tools,
give them all the context.
It can really help the AI produce a result
that's going to be exactly what you need.