- [Instructor] All right, let's kick off this section
by talking about how we can use AI
as our personal Excel tutor.
Now we're going to be focusing
on two different themes of prompts here in this demo.
First is using ChatGPT to better understand general topics
or concepts related to Excel.
And then we're going to dive deeper
into a very common and powerful use case, which is
better understanding specific formulas or functions.
So starting with general topics or concepts, let's kick it
off with something pretty easy and straightforward.
Can you please share a list
of some of the most common Excel shortcuts?
This should be an absolute layup for ChatGPT.
This is really common information.
There's a lot of public documentation for it to draw from.
And as you can see
we get a pretty clear response pretty much instantaneously.
Here's some of the most common Excel shortcuts
that can help you navigate
and work more efficiently in Excel.
So that's great, but you might be wondering, you know
why wouldn't I just google that information?
Which is a fair point
and this is where that conversational nature
of ChatGPT really sets it apart.
So now that ChatGPT understands the context
of our initial question or prompt,
we can follow up with something like this.
Can you narrow down this list to shortcuts
most commonly used by data analysts, for instance.
So it's going to say certainly here are some Excel
shortcuts that are commonly used by data analysts.
We're going to get a lot
of the same ones here, copy, paste, undo and save
and it looks like we're getting a few new ones here
towards the end that may be a little bit more
relevant for analytics, right?
We've got the alt shift and control shift shortcuts here.
We've got auto sum, the F9 calculation and so on.
But we can take it a level deeper, right?
And we can follow up again and say, "Okay, now
can you include both the PC and MAC versions as a table?"
And this is no problem for ChatGPT.
I love the format that it comes back with.
Super helpful little cheat sheet breaking down each action
or shortcut based on the PC and Mac syntax.
So this is information that you certainly could get
from a tool like Google, but the fact that ChatGPT can kind
of consolidate all this information in one place
without you having to scrub through different
search results, look at different forms or articles
or videos that makes it really, really intuitive
and really convenient as a research tool.
And then one more quick example with kind
of this generic topic or concept approach,
you might type something like this.
Can you please summarize each type of formula error in Excel
and how to fix them?
I'm actually going to drop this into a new chat
because technically this is kind of new unrelated prompts
and this shouldn't be a problem for ChatGPT, either.
It's going to give us these common errors
DIV/0 value ref.
And what I love is that it offers
potential solutions as well.
You can use functions like is number or
if error to solve value errors and so on and so forth.
So as an Excel beginner or intermediate,
having this information
at your fingertips is really, really helpful.
So next up, let's talk about specific functions, right?
This is a super common
really powerful use case that I tend to use ChatGPT
for quite a bit.
And let's start a new prompt here.
If you've been around Excel for the past year or two
you've probably heard of the X lookup function.
So let's start with something like this.
Can you please explain how the X lookup function works
in Excel?
And we'll see what we get back here.
So it's a powerful lookup and reference function.
It was introduced in Excel 365, Excel 2021 for Windows.
Here's kind of a quick summary.
I love that it drops in this kind of CSS code box here
where we can click to copy that code
straight out of the ChatGPT response.
And what it does, it starts breaking
down the arguments or parameters and what they do.
It lays out key features and benefits
which is a nice touch.
And then I really like how it kind
of recaps or summarizes the formula at the end, right?
It provides enhanced functionality for performing look-ups.
It makes it easier to retrieve data based
on specific criteria.
But if I'm brand new to Excel
or I'm still kind of in the beginner phases
this still might be a bit over complicated, right?
It kind of sounds
like I'm reading official Microsoft documentation here.
So let's do a little bit of prompt engineering here
and add some follow-ups to really hone in
on the type of response we're looking for.
So this is a tip that I love to use all the time.
I'm going to say now can you explain it
as if you were describing it to a child?
And note that I'm saying it here, I don't have to explain
that I'm looking for the X lookup syntax again
because ChatGPT already has that context.
And by giving it this kind of role-playing exercise,
I can hone in on the specific level of complexity
that I'm looking for.
So it says, let's explain X lookup in a simpler way
for a child to understand.
Imagine you have a big list of names, you want to find the age
of a specific person without having to look
through the entire list.
That's where X lookup comes in.
So you can see the, the words, the terminology
even the tone is really geared towards a younger audience
as opposed to an Excel expert or analyst.
So it's still accurate if you read through it
but it's just a bit more playful than my previous response.
And now one more tip here that I absolutely love is
using a prompt like this where it can say,
"Can you provide an example using some sample data
and show the formula syntax?"
And this is awesome because ChatGPT is actually
going to generate some sample data on the spot.
In this case, it came up with a table with names in column A
and ages in column B.
Very ubiquitous, common and easy to understand.
Example, it gives me an example syntax with an X
lookup function here, breaks down that formula argument
by argument and then again summarizes it here at the bottom.
And it's even adding kind of some
of the optional arguments here as well
to show some variations of the basic syntax.
So I'd give it a 10 out of 10 for this response.
It's accurate, it's intuitive, and it's really
easy to digest even for a beginner Excel user.
Now, last quick example that I want to share here
is using ChatGPT to explain what a specific
Excel formula is actually doing.
So in this case
suppose we have an Excel worksheet that looks like this.
Here we're looking at job salaries for different industries,
job titles and cities.
We've got the average salary in column D
year over year growth in column E.
And what we're doing here is producing a subset
of that data to show just the top 10 highest paying jobs.
And to do that, we're using a formula that looks like this.
This is a combination of nested dynamic array functions.
It's a little bit long, a little bit complicated,
especially if you're not an Excel expert.
Now suppose you've inherited this worksheet
and you're trying to reverse engineer what's going on here.
While in a case like that,
you could simply copy the formula straight out of Excel
jump back to ChatGPT
and add a new prompt that looks something like this.
Can you explain this Excel formula in simple terms?
I'm going to paste it right here and send it to ChatGPT.
And right off the bat, instantaneously it starts breaking
down what this function's doing.
It's amazing how powerful and fast this tool really is.
So it's going to start with the filter function
explain what that's doing.
It's filtering that range, but only where values
in column D are greater
than or equal to the 10th largest value.
That's correct.
Then we talk about how the sort function's working.
We lay out the different arguments
within that sort function.
And then I love this quick recap or summary at the end.
So in simple terms, this formula filters the data
in the range based on the condition
that the values in column D should be greater
than or equal to the 10th largest value.
Then it sorts that filtered data
in descending order based on column D.
Great response, perfectly clear
and perfectly accurate as well.
So to wrap up this demo,
let's talk through a couple of tips here.
Again, these types of use cases are best when
you're asking questions that have clear definitions
and a lot of public documentation to draw from.
And it's really important to be smart
about your prompt engineering.
So we talked about things like asking for visuals
asking for sample data, for syntax
for common use cases, and so on.
That's going to be really helpful to get the results
that you want.
And then again, I love role-playing a little bit
with the prompts to help modify and tune the level
of complexity that you're looking for.
Do you want the language to be appropriate
for a 10 year old or for a rocket scientist?
Now, overall, I love this application for ChatGPT,
I give it very, very high marks
for accuracy for these types of use cases.
And it's really just a great way to fill knowledge gaps
and learn about new Excel topics really quickly
and really effectively.