- [Instructor] Okay, so I've just spent
the last several videos hyping up the achievements
and capabilities of artificial intelligence,
and while modern AI tools are certainly impressive
and often very useful, they are by no means perfect tools,
and so we need to be aware of some common pitfalls
to get the most out of these tools and working with them.
The first and probably most concerning is that LLMs
are known to hallucinate facts with total confidence.
There's a famous case circulating on social media
where a user asked ChatGPT to perform some research
on a medical topic.
ChatGPT provided an extremely comprehensive response
and cited a number of research papers
and authors along the way.
The problem is that when the user went to go look up
one of these papers and the set of authors,
he found that they didn't exist at all,
so ChatGPT had made up a paper and set of authors
to support one of the claims that it was making
that was incorrect.
So you have to remember that these tools aren't perfect
and that you're ultimately responsible
for verifying the outputs of these tools.
If you make a big false claim
based on something ChatGPT tells you,
OpenAI isn't going to take responsibility,
you're going to be responsible.
Along these lines, it's also worth being aware
that solutions provided may be suboptimal
or entirely incorrect.
So in some cases, ChatGPT will help you solve
an analytical problem, it will just be a very bad
or roundabout way to solve that problem.
And again, these tools don't guarantee accuracy
and might provide inefficient solutions.
Another thing to be aware of is that these tools are broad
and often lack specific domain knowledge.
LLMs may not understand specific business context
or the why behind the responses they produce.
So when I'm working with ChatGPT
to help me with Python code,
it tends to do very well with the what and how.
What function should I use to perform this analysis
and how should I perform them?
But it struggles with the why.
If I need to filter some retail sales data
down to a specific set of products,
it will tell me how to do that,
but it won't necessarily understand why I'm filtering down
to a specific set of products.
And finally, LLMs are not capable
of common sense or human judgment.
Models need specific, objective inputs
and may miss critical context
that may seem obvious to humans.
These models tend to only be as good
as the data that we give them,
and if we are not giving them the full set of context,
they will often miss the mark.
And so after listening to all of these pitfalls,
you might be a little bit skeptical
about using these tools altogether.
And so I want to be clear that,
even though there are some very dangerous pitfalls
to using these tools, understanding that there are pitfalls
to using these tools is half the battle.
If we don't treat these tools as a perfect source of truth,
but rather as one additional source of input or information,
we can get a lot out of them.
So with that said, let's go ahead
and take a look at how to access these tools.