- [Instructor] Hey, everybody.
In this video,
we're going to talk about some of the most common use cases
for AI within the analytics workflow.
There are tons of things you can do with this technology,
and these are just some
of the most powerful use cases that we've explored.
You can use it to generate code or formulas.
You can use it to be a tutor
and explain some technical concepts with pointed questions.
You can use it for troubleshooting or debugging.
You can comment your code
if you have some that's particularly lengthy or confusing.
You can add comments there to make it more human readable.
You can optimize your queries or your formulas
for better performance.
You can generate step-by-step tutorials.
You can ask for data visualization tips
to help improve your data storytelling.
And you can use it to automate tasks,
research some specific technical topics,
or even generate sample data.
This list is not meant to be exhaustive.
These are just some of the most common
and powerful use cases that we've explored.
We'll also show you videos where you can dive into Excel,
Google Sheets, Power BI, SQL, and Python,
and you can get some more specific walkthroughs
of each of these different use cases in action.
I hope you check those out.
And just remember that some of these use cases
are already firing on all cylinders for these AI tools.
Other ones, the results may vary.
We expect these to get much better over time,
so you want to learn how to do these things now
so that as the tools progress,
you'll be right there with the technology
so that you'll be able to use these tools
to maximize your effectiveness as an analyst.