- [Instructor] All right, next up,
I've got a really fun demo for you.
We're going to talk about how to use AI
to actually generate new Excel formulas based
on descriptions that you provide.
So in this case
we're going to use some sample data here in Excel.
As you can see, we've got a grocery list
with items that live in cells B4 through B50
and our goal is to come up with two different calculations.
The first calculating the total number of items
in the list, and the second, slightly more complicated,
calculating the number of unique items only.
Now our goal is to see
if ChatGPT can produce the exact formulas
that we need to generate these two values.
Let's give it a shot.
So let's start with the count calculation.
And even though it's quite simple,
I still want to be specific and deliberate with my prompt.
So as you can see here,
I'm going to try to set some context right upfront
and say I'm managing a grocery list in Excel.
Can you please write a formula to count the number
of items in cells B4 through B50?
And by specifying the exact cell range here,
that's going to maximize the chances that I get a valid
and accurate formula in return.
So let's go ahead and give this one a shot.
It's going to say certainly to count the number of items
in B4 through B50, you can use the COUNTA function.
Here's the formula, go ahead and copy it straight
from the output here, drop it into Excel
and let's go ahead to E4.
Paste it straight from ChatGPT
into the formula bar, and boom, we got a 47.
So we can validate that number
by selecting the items in our list.
And right here in the footer, we can see the count is 47.
So off to a good start.
Now let's see
if it can handle something a little bit more complicated
and just give us the count of uniques.
Now before I jump back into ChatGPT, I want to talk
about a couple different ways
that I would solve this problem independently.
And then we can compare against the output
that ChatGPT provides.
So a couple different ways we could tackle this.
We could take the brute force approach
and then remove duplicates.
That's going to tell us there are 42 unique values remaining.
Or the approach that I typically prefer is using something
like COUNTA and UNIQUE and feeding it
that exact same range, B4 through B50.
I prefer this dynamic array approach.
It's going to give us that same answer of 42.
So we know the value or the output that we need.
Now let's see if ChatGPT can get the job done.
Now, important note here, I'm not going to create a new chat
because I want to maintain the context
and kind of treat this as an ongoing conversation.
What that means is that I can add a prompt like this.
Thanks.
Now can you write a formula to count the number
of unique items in that list?
And I can use natural language like that list
because ChatGPT has the context.
It understands that the list I'm referring to is B4
through B50 from my original prompt.
So let's go ahead and enter that.
See what we get back.
Says okay, you can use a combination of COUNT
and COUNTIF.
Actually this formula is a combination
of SUM and COUNTIF, but that's okay.
Definitely a different approach
than the dynamic array formula that we used.
But let's go ahead and copy that
and see if it does the trick.
So here we go and cell E6.
We're going to paste the output right into the formula bar,
press Enter, and we get 42,
which is exactly what we're looking for.
Now the only catch here is that this SUM
and COUNTIF approach is a little bit complicated.
We're actually calculating these reciprocal values
row by row, and then we're summing it all together.
It's a little bit tricky to wrap your head around
if you're not an expert Excel user and it's even harder
to communicate exactly what's happening here.
So let's see if we can kind of nudge ChatGPT
to use the dynamic array approach instead.
So we could say something like,
can you provide an example using a dynamic array formula
and see what we get back.
It's going to say, certainly.
You can use UNIQUE and COUNTA and check it out.
That's the exact result
that I had showed you earlier in the demo.
And we know that's going to produce the correct output of 42.
But this is a good point to pause
and remind yourself that you're going to get
potentially different responses
every time you enter a new prompt
even if the prompt is identical.
So I want to try a test here and copy this prompt,
paste it word for word one more time and see what we get.
So check this out.
At first glance, it looks like we got the exact same result,
but in fact we didn't.
The first time we got a COUNTA and UNIQUE formula.
The second time we got a COUNT and UNIQUE formula.
And the risk is that if we copy this COUNT version
and overwrite the original formula that we had in Excel,
you can see we're going to get a zero back
which is obviously incorrect.
Now because I'm a relatively advanced Excel user,
I've got a deep foundational skillset.
I know why this is incorrect,
and it's because the COUNT function is designed
to count numerical values
and the COUNTA function is designed to count text.
So by simply changing the formula from COUNT to COUNTA,
I get the accurate results of 42.
But this brings up some important points.
It's a great reminder why it's so critical to write specific
and accurate prompts and why it's still so important
to have that fundamental understanding
of what's going on rather
than blindly copying and pasting the outputs.
So let's jump back into ChatGPT
and see if we can rewrite the prompt
to try to avoid these issues right out of the gate.
So knowing what we know now,
we could try a prompt that looks like this.
Can you please write a dynamic array Excel formula
to count the number of unique text values
in cells B4 through B50?
And hopefully that gets straight
to the dynamic array solution, which it looks like it does.
It's using COUNTA, it's using UNIQUE,
and in fact, in this case,
it's actually adding a filter argument
which isn't entirely necessary
but it certainly couldn't hurt here.
So again, good reminder
of why prompt engineering is so important.
And then last thing I want to do here
is take that exact prompt I just wrote
and test this in Bard to compare and contrast the outputs.
Alright, so here we are in Google Bard.
I'm going to paste that exact same prompt
and see what we get in this case.
So it's going to think for a bit
and then come back and say, sure,
here's the dynamic array Excel formula to count the number
of unique text values.
It gives me this code snippet
which as you can probably tell, is just incorrect.
It's not even the right syntax.
And for good measure, we can try plugging it into Excel.
And as you might expect, we get an error
because this is not correct Excel formula syntax.
So again, that's why I tend to prefer ChatGPT
for Excel specific prompts.
So again, you've got to really,
really be careful when you're working with these AI tools.
So to wrap it up with a few tips, again,
be as specific as possible in your prompts.
Make sure you include cell references, important context,
that's going to help you generate accurate formulas.
And then most importantly, I can't stress this enough,
always validate the results and do a thorough QA.
ChatGPT isn't always right, and that's why it's critical
to build a strong foundational skillset
with these tools like Excel and SQL and Power BI and so on
and use these AI tools as a supplement rather than a crutch.
So overall, I think there's a ton of potential value
in using ChatGPT for these types of cases.
But as we've shown here, it can be very dangerous
if you lack that foundational skillset or understanding
or if you fail to provide clear prompts
or take the time to test and validate the outputs.
So very powerful tool, but make sure to use it with caution.